so here are the few accepts from man
Germany kaya and mostly it's from
Mullaperiyar suitor the number one
this is on a difference between
petitioner Arisaka
and an arahant conceiving here because
an untaught ordinary person who does not
see the noble ones who is unskilled and
untrained in noble ins dama who does not
see good man who is unskilled and
untrained in Goodman's dama from Earth
he perceives earth having perceived
earth from Earth he conceives earth he
conceives in earth he conceives from he
conceives earth as mine he delights in
earth for what reason because he has not
fully understood it I say and so here
obviously the element of Earth what
pretty much can stand for anything any
phenomena that arises in in experience
of petitioner through his senses so
anything that's perceivable anything
that is perceivable can be discerned
back down to the fundamental presence of
the four elements one among them or so
on so having perceived sight from sight
he conceives his sight he conceives
insight he conceives from sight he
conceives sight as mine he delights in
sight because he hasn't fully understood
it so on that very fundamental level of
perception of patinas perception of his
sight sound smell taste touches that's
already where he conceives it that's
where the mistake is
now this is not this is not a momentary
thing a sight of you to Gina there's not
lasts only for a split second a sight is
an experience it's a it's a
phenomenological experience like you
have a sight of something agreeable of
something disagreeable you've seen
something agreeable and disagreeable and
now your mind revolves around it for
example so that that sight is
and throughout for the whole time it
induces the Buddha would say it's Pizitz
changing while standing the same so so
it's not that the petitioner must uproot
at this subconscious momentary flux of
his consciousness incites him and
whatnot he needs to need to understand
the nature of the scene the nature of
the herd the nature of the sense in any
other way and that's that's the famous
bahia stood and seen there will be just
the scene when it's fully understood
well when it's not fully understood he
conceives the scene he conceives in the
scene from the scene he conceived seen
as mine and he delights in it because
there is an understanding of it so
that's another another reason to be wary
of of meditation practices that sort of
make people jump right into the sort of
like observation of sensations and so on
knowingly like for puta Gina because he
put - Gina spends time with his
observation he's spending time with his
own conceiving in other words just
perceiving things through your senses
cannot reveal you the truth because
that's exactly the problem here
Petrosian is just perceiving earth as
Earth but because of that he conceives
it his perception is not full
understanding so what / - Gina perceives
cannot undo his state of / - Gina only
what Petrosian understands can undo his
state of / - Gina so if a meditation
technique or practice is about just
perceiving sensations in in your body in
your feet and so on that has nothing to
do with understanding like you are
perceiving things ignorantly with your
ignorance basically it comes down to
that in other words perception cannot
free app' - Gina doesn't matter what
even he perceives Nibbana and actually
there the suit doesn't say that he perceived
the suit doesn't say that he perceived
Nibbana he thinks this navona is mine
and so on
and we said yeah that is Nibbana but
because he doesn't understand it he
doesn't attain it so it's about
understanding it's about understanding
of the over the five senses the nature
of it the manifestation of the sight
sound smell taste touches not about
perceiving the that the microscopic
little sort of quick moments and
catching them in their flocks doesn't
matter what petitioner perceives his
ignorance is there with that perception
because it's in the perception and
that's why this sutra is called the root
of all things Mullaperiyar suta means no
matter how far
putin's perceptions kind of ranges how
far egos how subtle it becomes it cannot
go below earth water fire and air as the
four fundamental elements and even if he
were to perceive them he will be
conceiving them because the problem is
not in the content it's not in earth
water fire air it's not in the sight
sound smell taste touch thoughts for the
matter the problem is in his perception hasn't
the problem is in his perception hasn't
been understood because of that it
conceives and that's the fundamental
difference between a patina and iris
abakan says big cuckoo is a training
with arasaka who still dwells aspiring
for the unsurpassed security from
bondage from Earth he directly knows
earth which means that's the fundamental
difference but to solve an ax or higher
has understood has understood the nature
of things he's understood the nature of
suffering his understood the nature of
perception he's understood the nature of
earth water fire and air he's understood
the nature of the appearing phenomena
because of that he's free from from
suffering the Four Noble Truths are
understood by knowing the way out of
suffering you are free from suffering of
course Ann arias Ibaka has to stop now
or rather make the effort of of
pronunciation in regard to the habits
that still linger from his previous
ignorant that now has been destroyed so
he's encouraged to not conceive earth he
is encouraged to not conceive in earth
he is encouraged to not conceive from me
earth and he's encouraged to not
conceive earth his mind and that
encouragement can work for him because
he has that reference point of having
and estudia directly knows the earth
which is what's in common with arya
Sabich an arahant
so for as long as he does for as long as
he fully doesn't develop the not
conceiving in earth from earth earth is
mine for as long as he doesn't fully
sermon the delighting in earth inside
sound smell taste touches he will he
will still be subjected to the leftover
symptoms of his previous illness of
being a petitioner but the illness is
uprooted even if he doesn't necessarily
make much effort in this life at the
Buddha said at seven most times seven
most occurrences of his lives the work
will be will be will be seen through by
the end of it but why wait if he if he
can if he can sort of approved overcome
extinguish all the lingering symptoms
from his from his prior prior infection
with with the Vidya he should do it and
then it says because the bhikkhu who is
in our hands with paints destroyed who
has lived a holy life has done what had
to be done laying down the burden in
reach his goal destroyed the fetters of
being from Earth he directly knows earth
same-same like an arias are the same
like a sotapanna
but he's also liberated from these from
all the fetters because from Earth
having directly known earth he does not
conceive it he does not conceived in
Earth not conceived from Earth he doesn't
not conceived from Earth he doesn't
conceive earth his mind and he doesn't
delight in it because he is fully
understood it so well it's not much to I
really said but it's it's it's obvious
first the earth the phenomenon that has
a reason in the experience needs to be
understood be whether you worry open it
down to earth water fire and air where
the sight sound smell taste touch needs
to be and this needs to be directly
known it cannot be just perceived and
then sleep that's the important point
here because people would often think
it's a question of perceiving a special
things novelty thing subtle things
that's how you discovered the sub truths
or some hidden realities behind but then
it doesn't get more hidden than the
fundamental great elements of earth
water fire and air yet even if those
things are perceived ignorance is there
because ignorance is in that perception
so for an arahant who has fully
understood it or rather who is directly
who directly knows it as as the sutra
says in the same sense sotapanna
directly knows it but then era honda
also made the effort and extinguish all
the symptoms of conceiving of lingering
concealing which are kind of gratuitous
foreign artists serviço the the main the
main dot of ignorance the main poison
and sort of infection that's done that's
uprooted but now he just needs to wait
for the wound to heal and that's what
would encourage here in order for a
wound of sotapanna to heal what the
previous wound of of being a photo gina
he needs to stop conceiving make the
effort and actually we draw the
conceiving x'
that he might still habitually well he
will habitually have to a different
degree then the the second bit is the
difference between the three in terms of
what they attend to and it's obviously
connected to this
here because an untold ordinary person
in particular who does not see noble
ones and his unskilled and untrained in
their dama who does not see good man and
his unskilled and undisciplined in the
dama does not understand what things
should be attended to and what things
should not be attended to since that is
so he attends to those things he should
not attend to and he does not attend to
those things he should attend to and
again so it's not a question of just
taking for granted what you've been told
you must pay attention to such as bodily
sensations and various types of
perception the question is understanding
the nature of what should be attended as
in skillful and wholesome and what
should not be attended as in unskillful
unwholesome but in order for like you
don't perceive necessarily you can't
perceive skillfulness of a skillful
thing nor unskillful mass of an
unskilful thing you can know it you can
come to those those those discernment
after after the effort has been made to
be understood as in wise a wholesome
thing wholesome and what makes it
sometimes something seemingly
unwholesome is actually wholesome thank
you for somebody who never practice
restraint saying no to sensual desire
every thinkin is very very unpleasant
initially and very painful and it can
seem very counterintuitive as well it is
going against the nature and against the
human mind against the body against
everything and it is and that's a
wholesome thing but then torturing your
body and in and in like extreme forms of
asceticism on a verge of death which is
like taking that against the body too
extreme well that becomes unwholesome as
well so things are not necessarily
defined by perception in terms of
whether they are wholesome and wholesome
but that can be understood and that's
exactly if one understands that one can
attend to it one knows what to attend
and as as the Buddha said petitioner
does not understand what should be
attended to
he does understand he does understand he
might have faith in it he might have
heard an instruction and now he's
attending to it to these things but even
so if it were to be done rightly he
needs to start developing understanding
an EXO he goes on saying what are the
things he should not attend to that he
attends to there are things such that
when he attends to them bein under
reason taint sensual desire arises in
him and the arisen taint of sensual
desire increases the other is intent of
being arises in him and the reason taint
of being increases the other is intent
of ignorance arises in him and there
isn't a the vineyards increases and
obviously consequently the things that
he should attend to but he doesn't the
things that when he attends to them the
other is intent of sensuality does not
arise and the arisen taint of sensuality
is abandoned same goes for the being the
taint of being in the taint of ignorance
so he keeps on attending improperly he
keeps he keeps attending unwisely so to
speak as in without without a proper
perspective so he ends up thinking was I
in the past was a not in the past what
was I in the past how was that in the
past having been what what it had become
shall I be in the future shall I not be
in the future what should I be in the
future how shall I be in the future
having been what what shall I become in
the future or else he seemed really
perplexed about the present am I am I
not what am i how am i where is this
thing where has this being come from
where will it go so you might notice all
these questions have one thing in common
which is they're completely
self-centered now obviously this is the
quite a condensed paragraph it's not
it's not that the day the person
actually sits on the chair and starts
thinking in such a crude manner was I in
the past was I not these questions
should be understood in a subtle level
of implication whereby when you're
thinking about something in the past or
something about the future you're
thinking in a self-centered manner as in
you don't question your own self in
regard to it you're questioning the
content of your experience you might be
even doubting but what you're not
doubting is that there has been some
sense of self you're not doubting that I
was in the past
or rather you know doubting the eye of
the question was I in the past because
was I in the past or was I not in the
past either way the question revolves
around the self-centered sense of I and
those questions as the Buddha said say
there is no like answer to them in a
sense of or you must figure it out
answer to every individual question here
that's been read on the contrary these
questions arise or other sense of self
and self centeredness arises as a result
of improperly attending to sensuality
nature of being and ignorant to making
them increase you result holding the
self-view you start properly attending
to them they diminish your views of
sense sense of self diminish as well and
actually yeah then here it says the next
paragraph when he attends unwisely in
such manner one of the six views will
arise in him the view that my self
exists is the actual truth myself does
not exist as the actual truth the view I
perceive self with self will arise in
him the view that I perceived not self
with self arise in him or the view I
perceive self with not self arises in
him and as non-hereditary pointed out
what petitioner cannot develop is the
view that I perceive not self wit not
self because he that arises in him then
he'll be a sotapanna so so he remains
fully self centered and established in
his wrongs of view as a result of
wrongly attending to these three types
of paints basically the sensuality being
natural phenomena
and ignorance and because he has he ends
up developing himself of you
he becomes subjected to aging and that
sort of lamentation pain grief in
despair that's it
so now a well-told noble disciple who
does the noble ones who is killed in
training in dhamma
who sees true man and is killed and
trained in the Dhamma understands what
things should be attended to and what
things should not be attended to sees
that is oh he does not attend to those
things he should not attend and he
attends to those thing he should attend
so he goes the same to repeat what are
the things he should he should not
attend that the things that lead to
increasing the sensuality being and the
ignorance hmm and things that are fit
for attention are things that lead to
decreasing of sensuality being in
ignorance and then because because he's
been attending properly he attends he
can attend further this is suffering he
attends properly this is the origin of
suffering he attends properly this is a
cessation of suffering he attends
properly this is the way leading to the
cessation of suffering when he attends
wisely in this way these fetters are
abandoning him personality view doubt
and adhering to behavior and duties so
yeah I'm just looking for a Pali word
here it's yeah so this is this is
already yeah this is talking about RF
Soraka who clearly she hasn't become a
sotapanna yet but already learned how to
attend to things like an errand as the
malapa yattawan imagine cup one said by
the way this is much america to exit
from it so Ann arias ibaka by having
understood what needs to be attended
properly having understood what proper
attention is having and having having
directly known what he is perceiving
then he can practice in proper attention
in regards to things as they present
themselves and bring the sensuality to
decrease being to decrease in ignorance
of decrease and then he can also attend
in the same manner about the nature of
suffering by doing so he will become
sort of Anna he will be free from the
self view from doubt and from holding on
to virtue and duty or behavior and
duties and says from a Germanic r48
furthermore because a noble disciple
reflects thus I'm endowed with the
nature of an individual who possesses
right view what is the nature of an
individual who possesses right view this
is the nature livid of the individual
who possess review although he may
commit some kind of offence for which a
means of rehabilitation has been laid
down still he had once confessed his
reveals in this closely to the teacher
authorized companions in the holy life
having done that he enters upon
restraint for the future in other in
other words he is his virtue he's not
doing his virtue he's not keeping his
virtue he has become it that's why if if
say laps and his mindfulness or some old
habits that are still strong or
something and circumstances press him
any commit some sort of offense for which he
commit some sort of offense for which he
needs to go through rehabilitation he
will confess it and reveal it and
disclose it to the to devise ones as in
to other areas to our hands to his
teacher or similar because he cannot
remain concealing it because he is it
it's an optional for him and and says
just as a young tender infant lying
prone it once draws back his hand or his
foot on a live coal so - that is the
nature in individual who possesses the
right view now back to Monica for there
are brahmins some recluses and brahmins
who perceive day when it is night and
night when it is day I say that on their
part this is an abiding in delusion but
I perceive night when it is night and
day even in his day
Riley speaking worried to be said of
anyone a being not subjected to delusion
has appeared in the world for the
welfare and happiness for many out of
compassion for the world for the good
welfare happiness of gods and humans it
is me indeed they rightly speaking this
should be it is off me indeed there are
they speaking this should be said so
this comes back to that as we open this
there the perception often you probably
people Maya must have come across pretty
much denying what you perceive as a way
of dealing as a way of overcoming what
you perceive and you will want to
overcome it because you bother by it so
people perceive things that cause and
suffering and so on so they think that
the way are the suffering is to study
nine the perception and you often hear
that even in the latest schools of
Buddhism the people who deny the reality
of things they would say they're
constantly changing on a subatomic level
and what not so what you look at it's
not really a real thing which is just
another word another way of sort of
veiling things in a method physical
ignorance of Maya and all hindus
teachings whereby that the reality is
hidden behind the appearances yeah the
buddha says well that's whichever way
you take that it's gonna be a body in
delusion when there is night he
tonight means what he perceives he sees
that as a real thing because there was
never a problem to begin with as again
Madame Madame Erica one Mullaperiyar as
we read in the beginning it's not the
perceiving that were sorry it's not what
you perceived it's the problem the
problem is in your act of perceiving
that misunderstood the misconceives what
being perceived so you can try and
examine and investigate as much as you
want the content and the molecular
compounds of the contents of your
perception still that's not bringing you
an inch closer to understanding the
nature of perception which is see in
order to understand the nature of
perception you need to be you need to
stop being concerned with the content of
your perception so first you restrain
the unwholesome content then you
overcome the wholesome content through
discerning the nature of what you are
perceiving not what you're perceiving so
there was this was madame afore
alright here is an interesting passage
quite useful - to remind yourself of it
magic I ate Jun de the idea the one who
has himself sank into the mud can pull
out another who has sank into the mud
that's impossible so it's quite obvious
unless a person is at least a sotapanna
as in somebody who is pertained to the
person to them to the direct knowledge
of another hunt as Mullaperiyar Souter
said above unless somebody's develop a
right view they cannot teach somebody
else in other words puta Gina cannot lead
in other words puta Gina cannot lead
another petitioner out of a state of
puto Gina a person who is himself deep
sinking into the mud cannot take another
one who is also in that mud right next
to him they will be sinking together and
it's important to maintain that criteria
because people people tend to water it
down through sort of an attitude of well
I am a petitioner but for as long as I'm
making these this effort my intentions
are good I don't mean any harm so that
means I can help others like you can
help others in in a very very relative
sense maybe pointing to the suitors and
so on but if you actually think you can
teach others in a way of direct way out
of suffering without you yourself
understanding the way out of suffering
that's a complete contradiction so the
best way to help others the most
compassionate way to help others is to
free yourself first to recognize the
first you need to step up find a way out
of the mud in the sinking mud and when
you do then you will help others you
will know exactly how to have others but
then you might realize that some of them
don't want to be helped so the idea that
one who is not sunk into the mud can
pull out another who has sank into the
mud that's possible the idea that one
who himself is unextinguishable
can help somebody else to become tame
and trained and extinguished that's
impossible